[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio this is Philip Winston my guest
today is laye Wagner Lane has been a
backend developer and data engineer for
the last8 years in fields such as
Hardware sensors data pipeline social
media analysis and educational software
Lane founded boot dodev in 2020 boot. is
a learning platform that uses game
design principles to teach courses in go
python JavaScript and various backend
Technologies Lane has a bachelor's
degree in computer science laye is there
anything you'd like to add to your
background no that's pretty good I don't
know how much we're going to go into you
know past work history but I spent a lot
of time in Python and go and yeah struck
out on boot Dev just a few years ago I
actually only went full-time on the
project end of 2022 but like you
mentioned uh it was kind of a side
project since early 2020 so okay great
today we're going to revisit the go
programming language the last full
episode we did on go was episode 202
Andrew jiren that was back in 2014 but I
believe much of it is still true
today but let's start at the top what is
the go programming language yeah that's
a great question so Rob Pike is one of
the original authors of the go
programming language Ken Thompson these
guys really came from a background in C
right and the goal with go as far as I
understand it of course I'm not one of
the authors but the goal with go really
was to build kind of a newer more modern
version of c and really stick to a lot
of like the kind of Unix philosophies
that went into kind of vanilla sea and
so the way I think about go especially
you know in 2023 what 12 years or so
after the initial release I think of go
as kind of modern C for the web okay
well go is a compiled language like C++
and rust what are the implications of
that in terms of the development process
or deployment or just what is it like to
work in a compiled language yeah yeah so
if you're coming from JavaScript or from
python working with a compiled language
can feel a lot different for several
reasons I mean first of all there's a
build step that you might not be used to
granted these days with like a lot of
JavaScript developers using typescript
there might be a little bit more of a
you know familiarity with with the whole
idea of building something before you
run it but what I found to be the bigger
difference and to be fair this isn't
like quite the same thing but like
static versus Dynamic typing right
almost all compiled languages at least
that I'm aware of have static typing let
go and that can be quite the mental
shift when you're moving into a language
like go now you mentioned that go is
it's compiled it's fast like C or C++
but there are a few unique properties
and I don't want to junk the gun on
questions you're going to ask but one
thing that's pretty interesting about go
is that it is compiled it is very fast
but I would not place it in terms of raw
performance on the same level as like C
C++ and rust so you're talking about
execution speed but the compilation feed
is also a factor so it is a compiled
language but what I read was one of the
developers of the
language was tired of waiting on 45
minute compile times I'm guessing that
was C++ but they didn't mention what
language so how did they try to keep the
compilation speed under control and do
you feel that was successful so
definitely successful I've worked on
some pretty large go
projects I don't think I ever had
compile times more than just a few
seconds which is absolutely fantastic
for like a for developer productivity
right it's kind of that that old
argument that was used a lot for dynamic
languages which is you know we don't
have to wait 30 minutes for a
compilation but it also is like really
great money saving thing like if you're
using you know GitHub actions or like
some sort of cicd pipeline to deploy
your code fast compilation is a huge
selling point I guess part of it's cost
but also it is you know developer
productivity if you're shipping to
production four or five times a day it's
really nice when your build and deploy
pipeline just takes a minute or two
instead of you know upwards of an hour
before you get feedback that like the
build failed for example so definitely
successful on that front and it is
important to keep in mind like the
difference between I want to be super
clear about this the difference between
compile speed and execution speed so go
does execute fast like when you write a
program in go that program will be fast
when you compare it to languages like
Java JavaScript python like I said
before I wouldn't place it into the same
category of execution speed as C++ C and
rust but as you mentioned one of the
trade-offs there is go compiles
extremely quickly so you know a
similarly sized program in Ruster C is
going to take much I want to say
honestly like there's at least an order
of magnitude difference in compile
speeds this might be harder to quantify
but I think of go as a smaller language
than some of the other ones you
mentioned do you think that contributes
to the compilation speed or how are they
getting this speed because it's
definitely sounds significantly faster
yeah absolutely so go is famously a
small and simple language and the go
team is very hesitant to add features
I'm sure we'll talk about this later but
like generics were pushed for for many
years before they actually added it as a
language feature partially because they
wanted to get the a AP right it was
something they were kind of retrofitting
onto the language but also just any
feature in general they're hesitant to
add because having a small and simple
language like really just has so many
benefits you know we don't have 17
different ways to write a for Loop in go
for example like looking at you
JavaScript right and because the
language is small and simple that makes
it easier to write a fast compiler right
just the natural complexity of the
problem is a lot smaller and I will also
mention that this is actually something
I recently learned on my podcast
back in banter I had the author of The
Rock programming language on and we were
talking about llvm and go does not use
llvm so llvm is basically this kind of
standardized way of compiling programs
and it produces very efficient very fast
binaries but compiling with llvm takes a
long time so one of the ways that the go
team was able to get faster compilation
speeds was explicitly by basically
building their own yeah we're going get
into generics in just a little bit and
then we're going to kind of walk through
other language features and get your you
know kind of summarize them but more get
your take on them and kind of where
things stand today with go development
but I wanted to ask what communities or
problem spaces is go popular with you
mentioned you know for the web in the
beginning I think there are also other
communities that kind of embracing go
can you kind of characterize where you
see go being used today yeah for sure I
think so I'm gonna like put words in the
authors of the go program language's
mouths forgive me if I'm wrong but my
understanding is that originally the
idea was kind of to make a new SE and I
think that that is not at all what's
actually happened after we've kind of
seen go in the real world where I've
seen it most is in backend web
applications and it's it's really taken
hold of like kind of the cloud native
Community famously like kubernetes is
written in go helm right kind of that
world Docker terraform Prometheus like
this is kind of the world of like the
cloud native go community and there's a
bunch of reasons for why go is great on
the cloud but I i' say that's probably
number one and then I would say number
two if I had to pick one is command line
tools so because go produces Standalone
statically compiled binaries go programs
are fantastic for like doing local
development on your machine when you
install a go program
there's no dependencies right when you
use npm or python you're always worried
about like is the script I'm installing
like what's the dependency graph look
like you know how long is it going to
take to install am I going to have
conflicts and even in like kind of the
world of C you know with Dynamic linking
you can run into you know dependency
problems the nice thing about go is
every binary is statically compiled so
you download it you run it it's going to
work you mentioned command line
utilities I think every other day I see
a new command line thing on Hacker News
that I wasn't aware of how do you do
argument parsing and command line flag
handling in go because in Python and C++
I've gone through sort of a rotating
number of libraries that handle it
different ways and it's non-trivial to
get all of the flag processing right
yeah so one of the major selling points
of go is this extremely rich standard
library and there's an OS package an
operating system package P AG that makes
it pretty easy to do your basic like
positional arguments and flag arguments
I'm going to be honest like the flag one
in particular I think positional
arguments is really great really easy
whatever the flag parsing and
go it's simple you can do it the
functional programmer in me doesn't love
like how mutable and stateful the whole
process is and I won't like spell out
exactly what the syntax looks like but I
guess the way I'll put it tur is it's
simple and easy but it's a little weird
from like a mutable State perspective
sounds like it gets the job done though
so let's start in on some language
features we are going to talk about
generics first because it's the newest
major language feature that I found and
in fact it's got kind of a history to it
we can go in so from your point of view
when did you start hearing the
discussions about generics and I can
jump ahead and say it sounds like it was
released in one .18 in March 22 so I'm
wondering I know the discussions went
back far but when did you start being
aware that they were working on these
generics so I started programming and
go it was either late 2015 or early
2016 and very quickly I started hearing
about generics so I think people have
been talking about generics probably
almost since the maybe even since the
language was first released right
because you come from another language
that has generic and you go oh like this
thing is missing right and frankly like
that's the experience of a lot of
developers coming into go is like oh
this thing is missing and that's by
Design again go is a very very small
language you can learn you know most of
the key words and language features just
in a few weeks if you're an experienced
developer so with generics I've been
hearing about them the whole time and I
think a lot of the resistance so the
first layer of resistance to adding
generics to the language was just this
idea of keeping the language small and
simple the second layer of resistance I
think and this is now just me
speculating on the community but like
for me was that when I'm building
backend web applications in go which is
what I was doing at the time what I
still am doing I don't feel the need to
use generics very of often at the
application layer like most crud
applications on the back end you're
taking data from some Source right from
like a rabbit mq or from some database
from an HTTP Handler you're doing some
sort of transformation on it and you're
shoving it somewhere else and so the
thing you're most concerned with is like
the structural shape of the data which
in go is really easy to represent with
structs if you're working with Json data
it's very common that you're just taking
a big old Json object parsing it into a
struct in memory you know nested structs
whatever and putting it somewhere else
so generics just don't seem to come up
all that often I think where the pain
the people who were more vocal about
getting them added in my opinion were
probably writing libraries where they're
trying to write code that's very
agnostic um they don't want to repeat
themselves 72 different times when they
want essentially the same logic for
different types and that makes sense to
me and I'm glad they took their time
that they got the API that they did
because I think they did a really good
job with it but frankly at the
application layer I still don't use them
all that often so going back to compile
time for a minute in C++ the template
system which is like generic
has these pretty complex features
apparently it is touring complete you
can write programs that run at compile
time essentially and that was template
metaprogramming recursive
instantiation all of these things which
I think go did not adopt so was do you
think again compilation time was a
factor in their implementation of
generics maybe LED them to avoid some of
these features that can kind of blow up
on you yeah and I mean so much so that
I've even heard like C++ developers
accuse go of like still not having
generics the idea being of course that
the generics that are in go are very
simple and if you look into it the go
team actually doesn't really call them
generics all that often they usually
refer to them as like parameterized
types and so it is a fairly simple
system although I will say I'm not an
expert on the C++ template system so I
have a hard time doing deep comparisons
other than to say I'm familiar with the
fact that c Plus+ can do some crazy
stuff at compile time one thing I did
read about Java in contrast to C++ is
they use something called typ arer so
the bite code doesn't have the actual
types in them and this prevents certain
optimizations I think I understand they
go although it's simpler system than C++
it does optimize down to the types is
that true yeah that's my understanding
to be honest like not an expert on the
compiler itself but I don't see why they
wouldn't in go you're using
parameterized types you're adding type
parameters to a function so like to give
you an example of what you used to do in
go so like before type parameters or
generics were released in go you
basically had two options you would well
let me give an example of a function
that you might use generics for so like
let's say you have a binary tree very
simple data structure that you're coding
up in go and this binary tree can store
arbitrary data types right like so say
the logic for the binary tree is all
going to be based on like the keys and
so all your sorting logic will be based
on like say integers if we're using
integers for keys but like you could
store anything in it you could put a
struct inside right you could put a
string you could put a map it doesn't
really matter what the values are for
the logic of your binary trait so in the
past with go what you'd have to do is if
you want concrete types like a binary
tree of let's say cars so you got this
car struct well You' code up the binary
tree and You' using all these concrete
types every wor you'd be referring to
this car struct and now you want to make
a new binary tree and in this one you
have let's just say another object of
humans right you want to sort the humans
in the binary tree you actually have to
duplicate all of that code like this is
what you were forced to do kind of in
the early days of go and so you were
basically stuck with either writing out
all the code by hand twice or what a lot
of people would do is use the go
generate command to essentially generate
the code twice with multiple concrete
types now with generics you can have a
type parameter and the go compiler will
essentially build out those two
different functions with concrete types
for you so I guess to answer your
question in a roundabout way yes it does
keep the concrete types intact and in
fact that's one of the best parts
because I guess you did have a third
option in the early days you could use
an empty interface which in go is
essentially like an any um if you're
familiar with typescript you got like
the any type the problem with that is
now at runtime you have to write code to
cast your types into and out of that
empty interface or that any type so to
answer the question yes generics made it
a lot easier and yes they do compile
down to concrete types at least in the
majority of scenarios that I'm familiar
with yeah I think that's what I read so
then one last point about generics why
Square brackets that kind of threw me
off when I was reading the code I think
um to point out I think C++ and and Java
use angle brackets I'm not sure what
other languages use but yeah that also
threw me off I think there were two
primary reasons that I read about the
first was that in go the square brackets
are already kind of a standard for types
in the sense that the go programming
language even before generics kind of
had this one magical data structure or I
guess you could say two magical data
structures
that were essentially generics but baked
into the language which are slices or
you know essentially Go's version of
like lists in Python and maps and when
you'd initialize a slice or a map you
could pass in essentially a type
parameter in the square brackets so you
know a slice of strings a map of strings
to ins we kind of had this standard in
the language of using square brackets so
so I think part of it was just like to
stay consistent with that standard I
also read something about the angle
brackets throwing something off with the
go parser due to like angle brackets
being used for other things like greater
than less than signs I don't know how
true that is though I just remember
reading about it on some
Forum there was a situation like that
with C++ at least back in the day where
you wanted to do two angle brackets in a
row and you had to put a space in
between them or else it would think that
was a insert oper or something like you
actually had to kind of fudge it or you
get a compiler yeah so let's move on
from generics and we'll kind of go back
to the top and go and try to talk about
for people that are less familiar with
it first maybe a trick question here is
go an objectoriented language or not so
to put it simply I'd say no
but now it's time for the huge caveat
the way I look at objectoriented with o
languages like the primary feature is
inheritance and inheritance does not
exist in go so if that's like the
criteria then like we immediately throw
it out and say go is not an O language
but there's some other really useful
ideas from oo that like go does make
good use of things like encapsulation
polymorphism there is really good
support in fact I'd argue that go has
one of the better systems for
encapsulation with like their package
system and how packages in go exist at
the directory level rather than at the
file level so if you're coming from
JavaScript you're probably used to
having to encapsulate modules at the
file level in go that same idea is done
at the directory level which I think is
at least personally I think it's a
easier thing to work with makes
organizing files it just makes it more
convenient sorry so do you mean that all
of the files in One Directory are sort
of glommed together as part of a module
or what do you mean by directory versus
file yeah essentially so in go at the
top of every file you have a package
name
and that package name is the same
throughout a single directory on your
file system so for example you typically
have a main package for your go program
and every go file at that level in your
directory hierarchy is going to be in
the main package and so to access
functions within that package you don't
need to like export them they're just
available within the package and the
nice thing about this in my opinion is
that you can organize your function
into different files however you like
and you don't have to think about like
the private versus right the whole idea
of encapsulation and trying to protect
certain data members or functions from
being called outside of the package
whereas like in a language like
JavaScript where you have modules at the
file level I think the disadvantage is
you might have wanted to split a file up
into multiple files just for
organizational purposes right but if you
do that now you have to do the import
export thing you have to like deal with
encapsulation at that level I want to
maybe come back to that issue of public
private I didn't even notice that not
appearing in the go that I saw but first
go has interfaces but not inheritance so
how does I guess a struct in go terms
how does it convey that it can Implement
an
interface yeah so strs and go are kind
of your
to objects or classes in a lot of other
languages they're a lot simpler right
they're kind of like structs in C
they're just collections of data for the
most part the weird thing is you can put
methods on structs and in fact you can
put methods on other types as well and
basically the way an interface works is
an interface defines a set of methods
that are required in order to satisfy
the interface so like the really classic
example in go is the Stringer interface
it's an interface that basically says if
any type has a DOT string method on it
that returns a string then that type
satisfies the Stringer interface and so
anywhere in my code that accepts a
Stringer I can now use that concrete
type as an instance of that interface
and one of the kind of unique things
about go that I think can throw
developers that are coming from you know
a language where interfaces are
satisfied explicitly is that in go
they're satisfied implicitly so in other
words if you have a struct and you add
that method that string method that
returns a string a method named string
that returns a string then
congratulations your type is a Stringer
now even though you didn't add any other
you know call out that you want to
implement that interface yeah that's
definitely curious to me because in that
example that seems such a common
interface that it's not a big deal but
suppose I have in my application three
four interfaces and I have some object
that or stru that implements two of them
how do I kind of keep track of that do
you just comment it you know is that an
issue I guess to keep track of what is
implemented I've never had it be an
issue to be honest I will say like one
philosophy that go developers kind of
have and this has been handed to us from
On High by like the go authors is that
interfaces should be very very small so
I think good go code idiomatic go code
right you'll typically see interfaces
with one two maybe three methods on them
but they tend to be very very small it's
a big mental shift coming from like an O
language where you've got an object with
just you know boatloads of methods that
get inherited from level to level in go
what we would typically do is use a
struct and that struct that concrete
type could maybe have lots of methods on
it or or maybe you even just use regular
old functions right that accept
instances of that struct and you'd kind
of save for the interface like truly
things that need to be used across
multiple concrete types and there's
nothing wrong with having an interface
that is a very small subset of what the
structs that implement it can actually
do if that makes sense this might be
related so I know there's something
called struct embedding I'd like you to
explain how that works but I think
that well let's hear how that works
first and then I can ask question yeah
struct embedding is a useful little
Quirk of the language so typically if
you have to like Nest some data right so
let's say for example this is a real
example from the boot Dev back end we've
got a user
struct and the user struct just just
holds all the data for a user in our
backend system right we've got email
password username handle created at all
that kind of stuff and there is a subset
of the fields on the user struct that we
want to keep private in other words when
someone looks at your public profile
page for example we don't want those
fields making their way to the front end
at all right we don't want to like
expose a password on that struct for
example so one option would be to Nest
these private Fields so in other words
we'd create a new struct maybe called
user private fields and we' in the user
struct create a private Fields key and
that private Fields key would map to an
instance of this nested struct that
would be a nested situation which is
something I'm sure everyone listening to
this is familiar with right you can
think of a nested Json object or nested
dictionary in Python embedded structs in
go are a little different it's where you
literally take the struct Declaration
like private user fields and you just
place that inside the struct definition
of the parent struct so in this case
user without a key so now instead of you
know private Fields colon user private
Fields the name of the struct you've
just got private user
fields and what that does is it elevates
all of those fields in the embedded
struct into the parent
struct so you can access them with the
dot operator at the top level so you
could just do like for example user.
password instead of user. private
fields. password it is a little wonky
because you actually can still access
them by doing user.name of embedded
struct so like user. user private Fields
do password you can actually access them
both ways but the nice thing is when you
embed in this way it's a good way to
like share a common set of fields
amongst different types so if you had
like a user and an admin and you needed
them to share 10 different fields
instead of typing that set of 10 Fields
into both structs and copying that code
you just embed it so a short question
first you mentioned this was Private
Fields but that's nothing to do with
like a private public keyword correct
yeah this would be more like a private
public in like security across a
network yeah
applications delineation I guess yeah
but my question before that was going to
be so back to the implementing
interfaces is it possible if I need to
implement three interfaces that I could
do that with three structs that are
embedded or
not so the embedding of a struct doesn't
really in any way correlate directly to
like the satisfying of an
interface so if we had a parent struct
with a nested or or I should say with an
embedded struct inside of it whatever
data is in that embedded struct could be
used in the method that the parent
struct would need to satisfy the
interface but like it's very agnostic
about whether that data just existed at
the top level or whether it was embedded
if that makes sense so you mentioned
struct methods is that where the
receiver comes in what is the receiver
Ino yeah exactly so methods are funny
things especially when you come from
like kind of more of a functional
background in a sense that you can
really think of a method as just a
function with one special parameter
right where there's one special
parameter that is the instance of the
thing itself so in Python they've kind
of acknowledged this and they just
always name that first variable in a
method self right so methods look just
like functions where the first parameter
is an instance of the object in go it's
very similar but that special parameter
is not just the first parameter in the
function it's actually off to the left
hand side of the function name so you'll
get like the receiver parameter when you
define a function and then the name of
the function and then the actual
parameters to the function that are not
just the instance of the method and the
reason it kind of needed to be this way
and go is because we don't Define
methods on structs within the struct
definition itself so like for example to
use like the analogy of python in Python
you would like define a class and within
the class definition you're defining all
of your data members and your methods in
go that's not the case you would just
Define a struct which is just data right
it's just a struct with key value pairs
essentially and then outside of that
struct definition is where you're
defining your methods on the struct so
that's why you have this kind of special
parameter off to the left hand side so
that the language knows that a method is
associated with a specific type so that
was sort of objects interfaces and
structs now we're going to move on to
one of the I think sort of Marquee
features of go when it at least when it
came out which is concurrency and then
just peeking ahead we'll talk about air
handling and then higher order functions
and then some other topics but starting
in with concurrency I think I remember
when go was released how significant it
was to have I think go calls them go
routines and channels and they're really
part of the language it's not a library
so I I wanted to maybe even going back
why do you think they included that
directly in the language I guess in 2012
when it came out sort of what was going
on that concurrency was such a big deal
and then moving on
to how do you use it today how often is
it used questions like that yeah so this
is a very unique thing about go I think
still today although not that I keep up
with every programming language that's
been released in the last few years but
go routines and channels are very unique
to go and you know when you compare Go's
kind of native support for concurrency
to other languages as you pointed out
with other languages you often have to
go to outside libraries to get these
kinds of features so first of all I
guess we could just start with like
what's a go routine so a go routine is
basically a lightweight thread so in a
language like C++ if you want to do
multi-threading you'll very often just
like spawn a new operating system thread
it's like the operating system will you
give you a new thread of execution to
work with in go
the go run time
manages those operating system threads
and what it actually does is Multiplex
go routines on top of threads so like
for example I could spin up let's say
two go routines and underneath the hood
the go run time will likely spin up two
operating system
threads the difference is I could spin
up like a million go routines and I'm
not going to spin up a million operating
system threads because operating system
threads are actually quite resource
intensive and expensive um to get access
to so what we likely happen is in go I
might spin up four threads I don't know
whatever algorithm it uses to figure out
how many threads it's going to spin up
under the hood but then we'll actually
Multiplex all of the kind of
computational operations across those
threads and handle that for you and the
nice thing about this at least from my
perspective is you get this really
lightweight way of doing
parallelization and the overhead of the
operating system threads is drastically
reduced but it's abstracted away from
you so you don't have to think too much
about how many threads are actually
under the hood usually what I find
myself doing as a go programmer is just
thinking how many CPU cores do I have
available to me right so if I'm on a
single core machine I know that even if
I spin up 20 go routines everything's
still happening in essentially a single
threaded environment but if I have 16
cores available to me I know that my
code will be kind of spread out evenly
across those cores as I need it to be
I'm not sure where CPUs were in 2012 but
I know the number of cores is just
increasing rapidly I think on a server
now you can get 96 cores maybe even 192
cores or something
and it makes sense to me to limmit the
number of Hardware threads I think in
systems I've worked on often you want
sort of n where N is a number of cores
or maybe you want 2 N or 4 n but yeah
you don't want a million certainly you
wouldn't even be able to allocate that
so how about channels I think you
explained go routines pretty well are
channels intrinsic to go tees or is that
another feature you can use yeah
channels are I would probably Define
them as kind of a separate thing and
they just happen to be really useful in
tandem with go routines so the most
basic way I can think to describe a
channel is it's just a go routine safe
cue or a thread safe Cee so a channel is
just this little data structure you can
create a new channel you can give it a
type so it's kind of like a slice or a
map in that sense you can make a you
know a Channel of integers or a Channel
of
booleans and you send stuff through a
channel so it's like a QE stuff goes in
one side and out other side and it's
thread safe so you can pass a channel
into two separate go routines which in
go the way you spin up a go routine is
just by calling a function and putting
the keyword go in front of it so like
instead of create user You' go create
user and that will you know call that
function in a new go routine so with
channels you can share
channels among different go routines and
the way you do concurrent programming
and go due to the use of channels feels
a lot different than if you're used to
using for example primarily mutexes
Mutual exclusion in you know a language
like C++ and the reason for that is
we're trying to optimize here for
communication right so we're trying to
communicate data from one go routine to
another rather
than try to kind of safely access the
same memory which is what you do with a
mutex right you you'd have some variable
and you'd lock access to that variable
with a mutex so that you know only one
go routine can access it at a time this
is like how you'd avoid race conditions
but in go what you're typically doing is
sending data across a channel and
channels are interesting because there's
a bunch of different operations you can
do with them but very often what you'll
do is you'll have one go routine sending
a value across a channel and another go
routine is sitting around waiting for
that value to come across the channel so
you essentially have this way to await
or block and wait for something to come
through a channel so it's very often
used in like data processing right we'll
take something like a rabbit mq or a
Kafka or a pub subsystem and kind of map
the incoming data into a channel and
then we can have many go routines all
pulling data out of the channel and
processing them in parallel
and because it's thread safe you know
none of them are going to get the same
copy of the data they'll kind of pull it
off one at a time round robin this kind
of model is is really useful especially
again kind of in backend web systems at
least that's where I've used it the most
you mentioned mutex though and I think
there's also Atomic operations do those
still get used or do everything map onto
go routines those do still get used
there's a sync package in the goh
standard Library there's also an atomic
package and so I use the sync. mutex
type from time to time the thing to get
right is like to figure out when you
should be using a mutex and when you
should be using a channel and I don't
know if I have like a really good
heuristic for that but I guess one
heuristic is if you have like a big
chunk of memory that you need to share
access to so like imagine like a big map
in memory M like a big key Value Store a
mutex probably makes sense but if you
have like workers items in a queue that
need to be processed like that's a very
natural fit for something like a go
routine and now your program doesn't
have to have any locking involved and
there's this great video I was watching
on YouTube a couple years ago where you
know someone was writing a service in
Rust and then they went and rewrote it
and go and what you'd expect is for the
rust version of the service to be faster
and I'm sure and the author of the video
was like I'm sure if I had written this
better the rust version would be faster
but go just makes it so easy to write
efficient concurrent code that his
version in go actually ended up being
much faster and I'm assuming because
there was just less blocking going on so
getting that right could be tricky but
for certain use cases go routines and
channels are pretty great to work with
again I'm not sure we can do the direct
comparison but I feel like in Python
things have moved from explicit threads
to async that has some
similarities so let's move on from
concurrency
and talk about eror handling this is one
of those cases where it was surprising
to me there are no exceptions in go is
that true that is true I mean you can
panic but as a general rule you
shouldn't do that and you know go
developers that are writing Ematic code
like very rarely Panic so yeah we handle
errors as values the only other language
I'm super familiar with that does a
similar idea is rust so air as
there is an error type and that gets
returned as a second parameter from all
functions or some
function yeah so the error type is built
into the language and it's actually just
a little interface it's a little
interface with one method called error
that returns a string and that's all it
is and by
convention when you have a function that
can go wrong for lack of a better term
then the LA last return value because in
go a function can return multiple values
the last return value will be an
instance of an error and famously Ino
you have this line after what's
seemingly every function called it's
like if error does not equal nil right
and if it doesn't equal nil then you
need to handle the error and usually
that just means passing the error up the
call stack so it's usually like if error
does not equal nil return the error
right so go is very much kind of a guard
clause-based programming language that's
kind of a pattern that you'll see in go
a lot which which basically just means
like a g function will very often just
have a bunch of if statements inside of
it that's saying like if something goes
wrong return early if something goes
wrong return early and then like getting
all the way down through the function
would kind of be considered the success
case yeah with exceptions although I
like them in some ways one of the
potential Mysteries is I'm throwing an
exception and I want to figure out who
is to handle that it might be several
layers up with no indication in those
intermediate layers that anything is
going on and so I'm guessing this is
meant to be more explicit and eliminate
that case where you're just throwing an
error and you have no idea who's going
to handle it yeah so for me the biggest
thing is just when I call a function and
go if it doesn't return an error I'm
reasonably certain that nothing can go
wrong so like the only functions that
don't return errors are ones without
side effects right like pure functions
they're's doing like some sort of pure
computation usually any function that
like accesses a database or does a
network call or something like that
almost certainly is going to return an
error and correctly as you pointed out
like this is my big frustration when I'm
working in a language like python or
JavaScript is that I can very easily
call a function and I have no indication
in the function signature that something
can go wrong here that I need to be
wrapping this
in a try catch or you know whatever yeah
that's actually a different point than I
was talking about but I think it's even
more fundamental that when you're
calling something in a language with
exceptions I guess some in C++ I think
you are supposed to declare that you ra
could possibly raise an exception but
it's at least back in the day it was
optional I don't know the details how
about the defer keyword that sounds to
me kind of like finally in accept
which is basically I want to run this no
matter what happens is the verb similar
or I guess it can't be similar because
there's no exceptions how does defer
work it's like very tangentially similar
in this just in the sense that you'd
kind of use it in the same way the defer
keyword is one of my favorite features
of the language and I frequently find
myself in I do a lot of programming in
JavaScript or typescripts wishing that
it existed so basically the way the
defer keyword works is you use the defer
keyword and then you pass it like some
function call some you know evaluatable
expression and it runs that or it will
run that before the function exits so
the most common reason to use it is it's
like cleanup code so you'll have a
function say that um opens a database
connection and immediately after opening
the database connection you'll defer
closing the database connection
connection because maybe later in that
function there's five different places
where you could possibly return from the
function right if there's a network
error you're going to return the network
error if you can't parse the data that
you get back from the database you're
going to return some custom error value
right and without the defer keyword what
you'd essentially have to do is close
the
connection at every single one of those
return every single one of those exits
kind of options so mostly used for
cleanup code so the last few topics we
were hearing about kind of go spin on
those features this one I want to talk
about first class and higher order
functions in this case I was kind of
surprised that go did have it because it
doesn't feel very see like it feels
maybe JavaScript like can you talk a
little bit about first class and higher
order
functions yeah so first class and higher
order functions like to kind of get
handwavy about it it's really like this
idea of functions as values right you
can kind of create functions as values
and pass them around your program just
as if they were normal pieces of data
and go does support this I think most
languages these days tend to support it
to be honest I don't think I've
personally worked with a language in
recent years that hasn't had some idea
of of functions as values it's really
critical that go does support this
because let's take the example of an
HTTP server and go so very often often
Ino you're building some sort of like
Json API right some backend service and
there's kind of two interesting things
about how you do this in go the first is
that you're using go routines as your
handlers which is like a little
different from like the JavaScript world
right in JavaScript you're kind of using
the async await like single-threaded but
non-blocking asynchronous operations to
handle many requests at the same time in
go you're literally just putting every
request on its own go routine so every
Handler can not only do asynchronous
tasks
efficiently like IO bound tasks like
going to the network or going to a
database but it can also do
computational tasks efficiently across
handlers and then the reason that first
class and high order functions are
useful is because that's generally how
we Define handlers in go so we're kind
of passing the reference to a function
into like some sort of routing library
and very often it's like the go standard
Library it'll take like a path and a
function as inputs to the router so
you'll say you know I want slash users I
want that to map to this function and
you'll just pass in the name of the
function this is my hdtp Handler
function so without first class and high
order functions I think that that whole
process would look a lot different okay
maybe two more features and then we'll
move on to sort of developer experience
and ecosystem um stuff like that so
maybe they're related pointers and
garbage collection so in C++ you don't
have garbage collection but you do have
pointers and in some languages you have
garbage collection and not pointers how
is it that go has both and do you use
pointers differently in go than in some
other languages and how often do you use
pointers good question I use pointers
all the time in go garbage collection
well okay so there's a couple things
here so first go is interesting in that
go allocates a lot of stuff on the stack
so if you're familiar with like stack
versus Heap go will actually embed
collection types like like structs
specifically on the stack and that's
really fast the stack is much faster
than the Heap the minute you use a
pointer and go you move to the Heap so
this is actually like the only reason I
bring this up is this is like a common
gacha go is as like a speed hack
sometimes people will use pointers in go
with the idea being or the theory being
well I'm using a pointer therefore I'm
not copying memory as it turns out in
most situations and of course you'd have
to Benchmark your specific situation to
see if this is applicable to you but in
most situations it's actually faster not
to use a pointer and go and to just let
the compiler allocate to the stack
because when you do move into pointer
land you do tend to move to the Heap so
that's like one thing pointers and go
are interesting it's like one of these
hotly debated topics people are really
frustrated with nil there's this idea
that like null and nil and none in
Python are like the billion dollar
mistake because we spend so much time
like around nil D referencing or
something being
undefined but I do think
that for the Simplicity of the language
pointers generally speaking were the
right call theistic idea use in go for
like whether I should use a pointer or
not generally has nothing to do with
performance optimization and it has a
lot more to do with mutability so when I
have a function that accepts a pointer
I'm expecting that one of the like quote
unquote outputs or effects of my
function is that I'm going to mutate
whatever value that pointer points to as
part of my function execution so like if
you don't want a value to be mutated you
should not be passing it as a pointer in
the general case pointer basically means
let's change this thing so continuing on
the theme I guess of Simplicity and
speed I know garbage collection in Java
has been optimized for decades I think
it's like a big focus of the developer
Community to improve garbage collection
how has Go's garbage collection been
since it came out is it considered a
weak point is it a strength so as a
general rule in my
experience a go program will use less
memory than an equivalent Java program
there's a couple reasons for that so
first as we talked about earlier go is a
compiled language and it compiles
directly to machine code you get like an
executable as your output you can
contrast that with most Java programs
where you're compiling to bite code
that's going to run on the jvm so it's
much more similar to like C C++ and rust
the difference is in go when you compile
to machine code there's a bit of extra
code that's included in every go
application and that is the go runtime
so you basically have your code and then
you have the runtime so that's why like
hello world and go can actually be a
fairly large static executable it's got
the whole runtime bundled in there and
the runtime is responsible for the
garbage collection my understanding is
that the reason Go's garbage collection
tends to be I shouldn't say garbage
collection but memory management tends
to be a little more efficient than some
other counterparts like Java
C python Ruby take your pick is due to
like the Simplicity of Stack allocation
so you know in Java you're taking full
objects and throwing them on the Heap in
go you're very often just allocating
primitive types or collections of
primitive types directly onto the stack
because their size is known at compile
time that that has a big impact on how
much memory you're allocating now of
course like you can go do crazy things
like you know make a giant m in memory
and then of course like your memory will
blow up and then you have all the same
problems stop the world garbage
collection that sort of thing but I
guess the way I'd say it is if you're
really concerned with memory then you
need to look to another language but for
things like high performance web servers
go is still it's in that performance
tier that is acceptable for the vast
majority of cases the stack allocation
is interesting in see there's a a
function that will allocate memory on
the stack but that's considered kind of
a bit of stunt programming I mean you
don't see it that you don't see it used
that often so it's interesting that they
built in the stack allocation into the
language the runtime is a good segue
into what I would call like the
developer experience so this is beyond
just the programming part if the runtime
is embedded in the executable one
tradeoff there is you can't up upgrade
the runtime of a program that's already
been deployed so like with python if
they come out with a new python version
I can potentially run that on my old
Python program I don't have to recompile
it or anything and it gets the benefit
of the new in this case if I have sort
of a directory full of deployed go
programs they might all have different
run times depending on when they were
last built is that true that's true but
I have a a hard time imagining a world
where that's not the easier thing to
manage in the sense that a deployed go
program there's no go code in a deployed
go program right it's just a binary so
like when you want to redeploy you just
build a new binary which takes a couple
seconds and slap that up on you know
your server and so generally speaking
I'd say it's actually quite a bit easier
because you're not worried about you
know if it compiles in the new version
it's it's going to work rather than
having to like test everything with the
new runtime or the new interpreter yeah
I guess the same thing holds for like
Dynamic libraries which I think have
fallen out of favor the original idea
was you could upgrade the library and
all the applications that were using it
would sort of get magically upgraded and
I think that proved to be pretty
complicated to manage and
embedding librar statically I feel like
is more common
today yeah like when you're really
constrained for
resources then you can save you know
disk space and whatever by doing Dynamic
linking like installing a program that
has Dynamic dependencies is going to be
a much smaller and faster installation
process than one where you've bundled
all the dependencies together but yeah I
think in web development in particular
what we've really migrated to over the
years is like we just want Dependable
builds we want to know that when we
deploy something all the dependencies
are there that they haven't changed so
like in the python world you know you're
using things like requirements.txt to
like lock all your dependencies in
JavaScript you have this package.json
dependency file and in go we just yeah
we bundle all dependencies that would be
dynamically Linked In Another compiled
language just directly into the
binary it means the binary is a bit
bigger like that's for sure the case but
it's not like on the order of gigabyt
so at least on the web where you have
fairly powerful servers that you're
working with the trade-off tends to be
worth it I think this is why go will
continue to struggle in the embedded
space right where C and rust and maybe
zigg now I think are going to do really
well because go does make this trade-off
that like you just when you're really
constrained for resources sometimes you
can't make that's interesting I don't
often think about embedded programming
but it's definitely a domain so going
back to the package and module system
and directory how do I structure my go
application from a high level is there a
tool that kind of spams out the
directory structure or do I just start
from scratch you usually just start from
scratch there's not like an official
directory structure there's a bunch of
conventions that have cropped up over
the years but like the simplest go
program is just a main.go file with a
function called Main and fmt do
printline hello world right so like you
can start really that simply and in go
it's pretty rare well I guess what I
should say is there's really no D Jango
or rails equivalent in go there isn't
this giant fully fledged batteries
included web framework in go most
services in go make use of primarily the
standard library and you'll import
certain third-party packages to do
specific thing so for example on boot
Dev what we use is the chi router for
HTTP routing which is very is really
just a thin wrapper on top of the
built-in HTTP package and go so you can
build a very simple HTTP server and go
that's like production ready just with
the standard Library which is something
that's hard to do in a lot of other
programming languages the CH router just
gives you like some convenience wrappers
around the standard Library so that you
kind of get a more declarative way to
define all your HTTP handlers so we use
the CH router and then we're using right
now a library called SQL C that allows
us to compile raw SQL files into go code
that makes use of again the go standard
libraries SQL package so this is kind of
the philosophy of the go Community which
is basically just like we don't have
this all-inclusive batteries you know
this batteries included framework that
exists outside of the language instead
we have a rich standard library that
everyone's kind of using to the extent
that they can and you kind of pick a few
third-party packages that makes your
life easier for database access HTTP
routing or authentication for example
related to external packages I think I
saw that go encourages you to use GitHub
or gitlab URLs in your list of
dependencies I'm wondering what are the
implications of that versus having a
package manager or a like in Python
there's Pi pie is kind of the
centralized manager we keep like
touching on all the things I love about
go maybe at the very end I need to like
give some gripes so people don't think
I'm just all rosec colored glasses about
the language but this is another thing I
love Yeah in go when you add a
dependency to a project you're doing
you're directly adding the URL to the
remote G repository of the code you want
to include and that actual command is
like go get so I'm in the root directory
of my project I do go get and then the
URL of some GitHub repository and
there's a few advantages of that first
is there's not a central source of Truth
like baked into the tool chain so like
with node you've got the npm
registry right and the tool chain is
aware of the registry and in order to
publish a package that can conveniently
be used by other JavaScript developers
you've really got to create an account
on npm pushup some code to npm and then
use it or in the case of other systems
sometimes you're not even pushing up the
code per se you're more pushing up like
built like object files or something in
go because of the fast compile times
it's really the compile times I think
that make this convenient because of the
fast compile times we just check the
source in as a dependency and then we
build from source which is convenient
for a bunch of reasons but one of those
reasons is I now have the source locally
in my project directory and I can
inspect it and look at it and see how it
works without having to like only rely
on the docs for example I guess
inspectability is a little more
transparent the other nice thing is as I
mentioned there's no Central source of
Truth so like even if you're using a
private G repository or even if you're
using gitlab or bit bucket or some
alternative provider it doesn't matter
the gotool change just cares that it's a
remote git repository although there is
that dependency on
get which is kind of interesting so near
the end let's definitely get your gripes
on go we'll do that when we're talking
about what's next for go so you can
register your complaints but finishing
up on developer experience what can you
say about the go Community where do they
hang out how do you feel it's been
interacting with them what do they like
love the go Community one of my favorite
podcast so if you're interested in like
go specific content first of all go is a
very small community that's grown a lot
especially in the last couple years I
think the release of generics and just
honestly just a bunch of podcasts
YouTubers people talking about go
recently has really grown the language
in the last couple of years it's really
started to pick up some steam but I know
the people that run the go Time Podcast
that's fantastic obviously on my podcast
back in Baner we talk about go a lot and
every interaction I've had with the go
Community has been pretty phenomenal it
is like a very centrally managed
community so you know if you take a
language like let's take Zig as an
example zigg is not really run by a
company right there's not like a Central
Main sponsor right like react has
Facebook go has Google zigg is like one
guy so that is one aspect to go that
I've I've heard criticism of which is
like well Google can just do whatever it
wants to do with go and that's true I
think that's a fair criticism although
it hasn't been a problem yet though I
guess you could make the argument with
any sort of benevolent dictator for Life
situation that it's never a problem
until it's a problem but I've been
really happy with with how the go team
does everything so far how about
learning go what would you point people
to as a starting point I think for any
big language there are many many
different starting points but if you had
to list one yeah so I mean obviously I'm
going to plug my own thing boot Dev is a
place to interactively learn go and more
specifically back in development so if
you're interested you can definitely go
check it out boot dodev I'd also
definitely plug the tour of go so it's
kind of like the official kind of Step
by Step through the language if you just
Google tour of go you'll find it I would
point to John bodner's book if you're
more of a book person I think it's
learning go by John Bodner that's a
great one I had him on the back in banp
pod recently and then I'd also point you
to Bill Kennedy another friend of mine
he's one of the co- founders of Art and
labs and he has a bunch of kind of more
in-depth Advanced tutorials for like
specific go use cases so like building a
web service in go with like his
preferred methodologies for example
those are a few that hopefully help I'll
put those in the show notes now what is
the future of go can you describe
anything that you know they're working
on and then what you would personally
address in the language or the ecosystem
what are the sore points of
any yeah so I actually don't know what's
coming up in the near term Russ Cox is
definitely the guy to look up and the
person who writes the blog post that
talks about what's coming and
his well he publishes on his own blog as
well as on the go blog so definitely
check out both of those places for like
the real source of Truth one thing I've
heard rumors of that sounds pretty
exciting is
memory
Arenas I don't know if like this is
actually something that's coming but it
sounds interesting and basically the
selling point as I understand it would
be like a drastic reduction in the
performance hit of garbage collection so
kind of different way to look at
automatic memory management that in
theory could really improve some
performance issues so that would be
really cool most of like the the gripes
that I have I don't think are easily
solved I think we're kind of stuck with
them they're things that I think you
kind of need to design for out of the
box but I don't know I could be wrong I
could be pleasantly surprised well how
about name one of them then yeah my big
one is
definitely the type system so in go we
are missing some really
fundamental typing ideas the big one is
enums in my mind or Union types right
algebraic data types whatever you want
to call them basically the idea that a
value could be of this type or this
other type right so like for example in
Rust when you return an error in Rust
you're not
returning two separate variables you're
not returning like the variable that
represents the success case so like a
user struct and the variable that
represents the error case just you know
an error interface you're returning one
thing and then you check whether or not
it is this or it is that which basically
results in safer code because you can't
forget to check the error so like in go
for example sure I returned an error
variable and sure it's pretty obvious
that you need to check the error
variable because it's sitting right
there in the line of code that you're
looking at so it's a lot more explicit
than like we talked about before you
know javascripts or a python but you're
not forced to unwrap that value right
you're not forced to check it by the
compiler and to me that is a weakness
I'm a big fan of static typing I'm a big
fan of essentially my tooling stopping
me from you know making these sorts of
mistakes and better support for enums so
I wouldn't have to do as much at runtime
would be really nice yeah that's
definitely the big one how about in the
larger ecosystem are there any libraries
or Frameworks or projects
that you're looking forward
to I'm really excited about SQL C I
don't know what the road map looks like
but I definitely want to plug it for a
long time I was using gorm or go omm as
like the way I interfaced with like
postest databases from my go
applications and like I don't want to
badmouth a project it's a great project
and I have a lot of respect for it but
it's a very simple omm if you have a
very small very simple application I
think you can get really far on orm but
there's a lot of disadvantages like
you're not getting type safe SQL for
example you kind of are writing your
sequel queries in raw strings and then
you have to like actually run them to
make sure that they're valid SQL SQL C
is so interesting to me and I haven't
seen an analog in another language
either by the way which I'm sure they
exist I just haven't seen them the way
SQL C works is fascinating you write a
raw SQL query which I'm a big fan of
because I like SQL and I like you know
having that full expressive power
and being able to use all the features
of my database but it basically reads
that query and compiles it into go code
so then in my application after I
generate the go code I can just call my
my functions to access the database that
was really exciting we have run into
like a couple little edge cases little
tiny bugs with it as you can imagine
just thinking about that project like
there is an incredible amount of
engineering work that needs to go into
compiling something as large as like all
of SQL into go but that's been my
favorite project so far okay Lane thanks
so much for taking the time today where
can people follow you online yeah so I'm
at Wags Lane pretty much anywhere I'm
definitely most active on Twitter if you
want to just like see what I'm talking
about so waglan on Twitter if you like
podcasts and you want to learn more
about go and in specific backend
development then the backend banter
podcast is definitely one to check out I
just had you Philip Winston on uh couple
episodes episodes back so that'll be
something to check out and then of
course boot. if you're interested in
learning backend development in Python
and go that's my current project okay
Lane I hope we nudge some people into
learning more about go programming this
is Philip Winston for software
engineering radio thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative comons
license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]